We sigh whenever we're about to come to a standstill
終わりなき旅の途中　立ち止まりそうな時
Owarinaki tabi no tochuu tachidomarisouna toki
While moving on this endless journey.
深いため息こぼす　僕らは
Fukai tameiki kobosu bokura wa
Everytime we lunge for it, it escapes and flies off.
掴みかけてはまた離れていった
Tsukamikaketewa mata hanareteitta
But now, there's nothing to be afraid of
でも今はもう何も恐れることはない
Demo ima wa mou nanimo osoreru koto wa nai
The powerful ties that bind our hearts
心を繋ぐ強い絆は
Kokoro wo tsunagu tsuyoi kizuna wa
Will never come loose.
けして解けはしないさ
Keshite hodoke wa shinai sa
After a lifetime of searching, we finally arrived
探し続けて辿り着いた
Sagashitsuzukete tadoritsuita
Here, where the period lies.
この場所で Period に
Kono basho de piriodo ni
Let's change all our sorrow and rage to power.
悲しみ怒り 力に変えて
Kanashimi ikari chikara ni kaete
Destiny is right within our reach.
運命はすぐそばに
Unmei wa sugu soba ni
So you're suggesting Major General Armstrong had a hand in Lieutenant General Raven's disappearance?
アームストロング少将が
レイブン中将失踪に関係していると？
Most likely.
おそらくな
But I'm sure she left no evidence.
だが　証拠を残す愚は犯すまい
確かに
You're right.
Ah, well. Our job is to take over this fort...
まあいい
我々の仕事はこの砦を掌握することだ
...while that fox is being investigated in Central by a herd of tigers.
あの女狐が
セントラルで虎の群れに囲まれている間にな
Oh, if it isn't the Major General.
これはこれは　少将閣下
ちっ　貴様がセントラル勤務とはな
I still can't believe you were transferred to Central.
What connections did you use?
どんなコネだ？
I believe it's simply an honest display of my capabilities.
いや　実力じゃないですか？
青二才がよく言う
Says the fresh meat.
What brings you here today?
今日は　どのようなご用事で？
I've been summoned by the Führer President.
大総統閣下に呼ばれて来た
I may not be able to return to Briggs for a while.
北へはしばらく戻れんかもしれんな
"For a while"?
戻れない…
Then I'm going to have to take you to dinner at least once.
では　ぜひ一度食事でも
Is it your treat?
おごりか？
貴様が破産するまで食べていいなら行ってやるぞ
If you'll let me eat until you go bankrupt, I don't mind going for dinner.
食事はあきらめます…
I guess I'll give up on the meal, then...
Both your wallet and your balls are pea-sized, I see.
なんだ　肝と財布の小さい男だな
How about some flowers instead?
代わりに花などいかがでしょう？
ふん
There are many great florists in Central, after all.
セントラルにはいい花屋が多いですから
そうか
I see.
You may enter.
入りたまえ
Yes, sir.
はっ
Now, Major General Armstrong...
さて　アームストロング少将
...let me hear more about
Lieutenant General Raven's disappearance.
レイブン中将行方不明の件について聞こう
What did you do?
何をした？
I won't be able to hide this.
これは隠しきれんな
Why would a man as great as you choose to place a fool like Raven by his side?
閣下ともあろうお方があのような粗忽者を
傍らに置いておかれるとは
どういうことでしょうか？
So you got rid of him?
だから　始末したのかね？
You don't need him.
いらんでしょう　あれは
あのような口の軽い輩がいては
Having a subordinate with such a loose tongue would do you no good.
閣下のためになりません
What did Lieutenant General Raven tell you?
レイブン中将は君に何を言った？
Something about an immortal army...
不死の軍団
...the history of this country, and your real identity.
この国の成り立ち　閣下の正体
聞きもしないことを　いろいろ教えてくれました
He told me many things I didn't even ask for.
うむ
君はそれを聞いたうえで
So you still chose to respond to
my summons after hearing all that?
呼び出しに応じたというのかね？
Yes, to request the seat the idiot had been placing his ass on.
はい　あのアホが座っていた席をもらい受けるために
Interesting, as expected of you.
おもしろい　それでこそだ
Very well. You may have the position.
よろしい　君に席を与えよう
In exchange, I'll have one of my men govern over Briggs. Are you fine with this?
代わりにブリッグズ砦は
私の手の者が治めるが　よいな？
As you wish, sir.
どうぞ　ご随意に
They are powerful soldiers I trained with great care.
手塩にかけた　屈強な兵たちです
I'm sure you'll like them.
必ずや　閣下のお気に召すでしょう
Interesting. Do your best, human.
気に入ったぞ
したたかにあがけよ　人間
"Nothing ventured, nothing gained."
「虎穴に入らずんば　虎子を得ず」
So the Major General ventured into the enemy's lair by her own will.
少将は自ら虎穴に入られましたか
Yeah. This place also belongs to them now.
ああ　ここも連中のものだ
But they're unaware...
ですが　ヤツらは知らない
...Briggs is a giant monolith that can act with a united will, even if its master happens to be away.
主が不在であろうと
一つの意志の下に動くことができる巨大な一枚岩
それが　ブリッグズ砦
うむ　ここからは熊と虎の食らい合いよ
From here on, it's a war between bears and tigers.
Is that seat free?
そこ空いているかね？
Yes.
どうぞ
How's your work progressing?
お仕事は　どうです？
As you can see,
見てのとおりだ
I can't finish everything unless I multitask during my meals, as well.
食事中もやっておかないと追いつかんよ
And you?
そっちはどうだ？
There's so much to memorize; I'm fairly busy.
覚えることが多くて
それなりに忙しいです
でも　閣下は仕事が早いので助かります
But the Führer President does his job very quickly, so I do not have to worry about that.
He doesn't loaf either, unlike a certain someone.
何よりサボりませんし
I have a feeling this topic is heading in a direction I don't like.
おもしろくない話になりそうだ
That reminds me...
そういえば…
Scar is apparently up north.
スカーが今北にいるとか
エルリック兄弟も北ですよ
So are the Elric brothers.
I see.
そうか
My old classmates, Lucy and Ian, are also up north.
北には今同期のルーシーとイアンがいて
They tell me many things.
いろいろ教えてくれます
へえ～
確か　春には北と東の合同演習があるな
If I recall, the north and the east will be holding joint exercises in the spring.
Yes, we've been defeated countless times by Major Miles and Captain Buccaneer.
ええ　マイルズ少佐とバッカニア大尉には
何度もしてやられましたよね
Miles... Buccaneer...
マイルズ　バッカニア
York, Ida, and Sugar, too.
ヨークも　アイダとシュガーも声を掛けられてと…
Havoc, Oscar, Mike, Uni, Nora, Charley...
ハボック　オスカー
マイク　ユニ　ノラ　チャーリー
Uni again, then Lucy...
再度ユニで　ルーシー…
Uni comes again, then next... is Sterling!
ユニが来て
最後はスターリング！
"Selim Bradley is Homunculus".
「セリム·ブラッドレイは人造人間」
I guess there's no way that can't  be true.
ありえないなんてことはありえないか
Just what is about to happen here in Central?
一体　このセントラルで何が起きようとしている…
Boy.
少年
Hey, you over there.
ねえ　そこの君
あっ…　いけね！
Oh, crap!
大丈夫
Don't worry.
Over here.
こっちこっち
うん？　なんだ
What the hell?
Come on.
おいおい
君ね　ちょっと驚くとか何かしたらどうかな
Aren't you at least a little surprised?
If I do get surprised, will you give me something?
驚いたらなんかくれるのか？
I guess you're always at ease. I like you.
う～ん…　ものおじしないのは気に入った
What's your name?
君の名前は？
Slave Number 23.
２３号
I didn't ask for a number. I want your real name.
番号じゃなくてほんとの名前を教えてくれよ
I don't have a name. I'm a slave.
ねぇよ　奴隷だもん
Slave?
奴隷…
People who are stripped of their rights and freedom, and are exchanged as possessions in conveyance?
権利や自由は与えられず所有物として
譲渡売買される人間
Conveyance?
譲渡？
To transfer property and rights and such.
財産権利等を他人に譲り渡すこと
君頭悪いんだな
You're not very bright, are you?
Shut up!
ほっとけ！
I don't understand how I was born from someone like you.
なぜこんなのから私が生まれたのか
さっぱり分からない
You're the one who gave me blood, aren't you?
君だろ？　私に血をくれたのは
They did take a lot of blood from me to use for experiments...
そういや実験に使うって　かなり…
君が血をくれたから
I was born because you gave me blood.
私はこの世に生まれ出た
Thank you. Umm...
ありがとう　え～っと…
"Slave Number 23" just sounds too cold.
やっぱり２３号では素っ気がない
I'll give you a name, then.
私が名前を付けてあげよう
Who the hell do you think you are?
何様だお前は
立派なのがいいだろう
Don't you want a cool name? Let's see...
そうだなぁ　う～ん…
Teo... Teofrastus Bombastus.
テオ…
テオフラストゥス·ボムバストゥス
Too long.
長ぇよ
えっ？
Ah, it can't be too long; else you won't be able to memorize it. You're dumb, after all.
あっ　そうか　長いのは覚えられないんだね
頭悪いから
頭悪い言うな！
Quit saying that!
それじゃあ　ヴァン
Then how about Van?
Van Hohenheim.
ヴァン·ホーエンハイムでどうだろう
Van Hohen, eh?
ヴァン·ホーエンか…
I should be able to remember that.
それくらいなら覚えられるな
You spell it like...
つづりは…　って
Wait, do you know how to read and write?
そうだ君文字の読み書きは？
I don't need to know to work.
そんなものできなくたって　仕事はできる
The work of a slave, right?
奴隷の仕事
Don't you want freedom and rights?
自由と権利が欲しくないか？
Do you plan on ending your life as a slave without gaining basic human rights?
人間としての権利を手に入れないまま
奴隷で一生を終える気か？
That's the same as being in this stuffy flask.
それでは息苦しいフラスコの中にいるのと同じだ
I'm going to share my knowledge with you, Van Hohenheim.
知識を与えてやろう
ヴァン·ホーエンハイム
Hey... What are  you?
なあ…　お前はなんだ？
What should I call you?
なんと呼べばいい？
The Little One Inside the Flask. So... call me "Homunculus".
フラスコの中の小人
「フラスコの中の小人」とでも呼んでもらおうか
All was created from one, and it eventually returns to one.
すべてのものは一からつくり出され
一へと還っていく
In other words, one is all.
すなわち　一は全
All exists due to one...
一により全があり…
...and all exists within one.
一の中に全がある
If one does not contain all, then there exists nothing.
一が全を含まなければ
すべては無なり
合格だ
You pass.
You're now a fine alchemist, Hohenheim.
もはや立派な錬金術師だな
ホーエンハイム
I'm still not good enough to be on my own.
まだまだ助手の域は出ません
My abilities are far beneath yours, Master.
ご主人様の腕前には程遠いです
ほう～
You know, I'm really thankful.
感謝しているよ
For what?
何が？
Because you gave me knowledge,
I'm able to live a good life like this.
知識をくれたお陰で
こうしていい暮らしができている
I'm also happy to be in Master's favor.
ご主人様の覚えも　めでたい
いずれ誰かと結婚し
It may be possible that I can marry someone in the future and start my own family.
家庭を持つことだって夢じゃない
A family, eh?
家庭ねぇ…
Humans are inconvenient creatures, aren't they?
人間は不便だな
そうやってコミュニティーを持って繁殖せねば
The species can't live on unless they all create a community and expand.
種を存続できない
Don't talk like that.
繁殖とか言うな
お前から見たらバカバカしいかもしれないけど
It may be stupid in your eyes,
but having friends and family...
家庭とか仲間とか
...may bring one happiness.
そういうものに幸せってのがあったりするんだよ
For us humans, that is.
オレたち人間は
Really?
そんなものかねぇ
Then what do you consider happiness?
じゃあ　お前の幸せってなんだ？
Let's see...
そうだな
I don't want to be too greedy, but I guess being able to leave this flask would make me happy.
ぜいたくは言わないが
このフラスコから出られる身になれば　幸せかな
不老不死…
Immortality...
どうして権力と栄華を極めたヤツは
I wonder why fools who gained ultimate authority and prosperity begin to wish for that.
そっちにいくのかねぇ
口を慎め！
Mind your tongue!
You're talking to the King!
陛下の御前であるぞ！
If you continue to be disrespectful, I'll break the flask!
無礼を働けば
そのフラスコたたき割る！
君たちが知りえない知識の源を壊すのかい？
You're going to destroy the source of the knowledge you don't know about?
無駄口はいい
Cease your prattling.
不老不死できるのかできないのか
Can you make me immortal or not?
Growing impatient as you age, huh?
老いによる焦りか悲しいね
How sad, King of Xerxes.
クセルクセス王
いいよ～
Fine, I'll tell you how to achieve immortality.
不老不死の方法を教えてやろう
What's with the construction?
なんの工事なんだ？
灌漑用水路だよ
We're making a waterway for irrigation.
国王の命で　国中に水路を張り巡らせるんだ
The King ordered a waterway to extend around the entire country.
さすがクセルクセス王
Nothing less to be expected from the King of Xerxes.
わしら下々のこともよくお考えだ
He even thinks about commoners like us.
そうだな
That's right.
いいか　一人残らず始末しろ
Kill them all. Understood?
はっ！
Yes, sir!
急げ　早く！
Hurry! Waste no time!
早く血の紋を刻むのだ
Hurry and carve a bloody crest into the land!
The village to the north was raided?
北の村が 襲われたんだって？
一人残らず殺されたって
I heard everyone there was killed.
この前は西の村だ
And the same thing happened in the village to the west last time.
I wonder who's behind it...
何者の仕業なんだろう…
ひどい話だ
How terrible.
大変だねぇ
Yeah, how awful.
Your Majesty, the transmutation circle is finally complete.
陛下 念願の錬成陣が完成いたしました
うむ 長かった ようやくだ
Truly, it has been a long time.
これで　よいのだな？
This is all we need to do, right?
ああ　不老不死になれるよ
Yeah, you'll be able to become immortal.
すごいな
That's amazing.
国王が不老不死になるんだ
The King is going to become immortal.
おお…
世紀の瞬間ってやつだな
I guess it's what they call the turning point of the century.
おおっ　これが不老不死…
So this is immortality...
What's this?!
どういうことだ！？
中心にいる我々には害は及ばないと…
You said that since we're in the center of it, we wouldn't be harmed!
なんだ？
What?
何が起こっている！？
What's happening?!
Hey! Homunculus!
おい　ホムンクルス！
錬成陣の真の中心は
The true center of the transmutation circle is where you're standing right now.
君が立っている　ここだよ
何っ！？
What?!
私の中の君の血を使って
I opened the gate using your blood inside of me.
扉を開けさせてもらった
血を分けた家族
You're a relative that shares my blood, Hohenheim!
ホーエンハイムよ
今　君と私がすべての中心だ！
Right now, you and I are at the center of the world!
陛下！
Your Majesty!
ご主人様！
Master!
死んでる
He's dead.
誰か　いないのか？
Is anyone here?!
ウィラード！　メヒティルト！
Willard!
Mechthild!
ラインマイル！
Linemile!
トーニ！　メイヨー！
Tony!
Meiyou!
誰か…　返事をしてくれ
Please... Someone, say something.
無理だな　皆魂を抜かれている
It's no use. Everyone has had their souls taken from them.
国王陛下！
Your Majesty!
ご無事でしたか…
You were all right...
So...
どうだ？
その体　具合はいいか？
...How do you like your new body?
It's... me...
オレが…　いる…
I created a body for myself using
the information stored in your blood.
君の血の情報をもとに
入れ物をつくらせてもらったよ
ふぅ～　やれやれ
Finally, I can walk with my own two feet.
やっと　自分の足で歩ける
You're... Homunculus?
お前　ホムンクルスなのか？
どういうことだ！ 何をした！？
What is this?! What did you do?!
In return for you giving me blood, I gave you a name and shared my knowledge with you.
血をくれた礼に
名を与えた　知識を与えた
I also gave you an eternal body.
そして　朽ちぬ体を与えた
朽ちぬ？
Eternal?
Try focusing all of your consciousness into yourself.
自分の中に意識を集中してみろ
Can't you hear the voices?
聞こえるだろう？
お前が不死身になるための引き換えになった
The voices of all the people, who lived in this country, sacrificed for your immortal body.
この国のすべての人間の声が
Well, half of them went to me.
まっ　半分は私がもらったがね
協力感謝するよ　ホーエンハイム
Thanks for your help, Hohenheim.
ホーエンハイムさん？
Mr. Hohenheim?
やっぱり！
It really is  you!
うん？
いや　まさか　エドとアルの親御さんだったなんて
Wow, I didn't know you were Ed and Al's father.
そちらこそ息子たちの師匠だったとは…
I didn't expect you to be the master of my sons, either...
大変世話になったようで
I hear you did a lot for them.
いえいえ　気にしないで
No, not at all.
イズミさん？
Miss Izumi?
Are you all right, Izumi?!
イズミ　大丈夫か！？
今　薬を…
I'll get your medicine...
Let me take a look at her.
診てあげよう
私は医術を少しかじっている
I know a thing or two about medicine.
おお…
大丈夫　いつものだから
Don't worry, this isn't anything new.
ん！？　これは大丈夫じゃない
This is certainly something to worry about.
シグさん　車を拾ってきてください
Mr. Sig, please get a cab.
えっ？
急いで！
Hurry!
わ…　分かった！
R-Right!
イズミさん
Miss Izumi...
あなた　真理を見たね？
You saw the truth, didn't you?
何を犠牲にした？
What did you sacrifice?
ごまかさないでくれ
Please don't try to hide it.
中を持っていかれた
They took a few of my organs.
死んだ子供をよみがえらせようとして
I tried to revive my dead baby.
そうか
I see.
うん　そうか…
I see...
ちょっと失礼
If you'll excuse me.
イズミ　しっかりしろ！
Izumi! Hang in there!
Izumi!
イズミ！
あんた　落ち着いて
Calm down, Dear. I'm fine.
大丈夫だから
腹刺されたんだぞ！
You were stabbed in the stomach!
でも呼吸が楽になった
But I can breathe more easily now.
見せてみろ
Show me your wound.
傷ないよ
There's no wound.
That can't be!
そんなバカな…
The organs that were taken are the proof of your sins, so I can't bring them back.
持っていかれた臓器は
あなたの罪の証しだから戻せないけど
But I rearranged your insides a bit to ease the flow of blood.
腹の中をちょいと整理して
血の流れをよくしといた
Miss Izumi, you can't die just yet.
イズミさん　あなたはまだ倒れちゃいけない人だ
ホーエンハイム　あなた
Hohenheim...
Just... what exactly are  you?
一体何者？
私は
I'm a human by the name of Van Hohenheim...
ヴァン·ホーエンハイムという
人間の形をした
賢者の石だ
A philosopher's stone in human form.
The promise we never made
交わしたはずのない約束が
Kawashita hazu no nai yakasoku ga
yet again
今日も
Kyou mo
tries to snatch our future away from us.
僕らの未来を奪おうとする
Bokura no mirai wo ubaou to suru
Why is it that we can't rejoice
欲しがっていたものを手にしても
Hoshigatteita mono wo te ni shitemo
straight from the heart
素直に
Sunao ni
when we obtain something we've always been after?
うまく笑えないのはなぜだろう
Umaku waraenai nowa nazedarou
The overflowing tears aren't from feebleness or remorse.
あふれる涙は　弱さや後悔じゃない
Afureru namida wo yowasa ya koukai ja nai
They're fragments born from agony.
イタミが生んだカケラで
Itami ga unda kakera de
Of all the moments and destinies,
どんな瞬間だって運命だって
Donna shunkan datte unmei datte
I realized there's one absolute certainty.
ひとつだけ確かなものがあると知った
Hitotsu dake tashika na mono ga aru to shitta
Even if things get tough and I'm at my limit
限界だって困難だって
Genkai datte konnan datte
I refuse to give up.
あきらめたくないよ
Akirametakunaiyo
Please, don't let go.
このまま離さないで
Konomama hanasanaide
I can feel the warmth of your right hand
かたく握りしめた　君の右手のぬくもり
Kataku nigirishimeta kimi no migite no nukumori
where it's tightly joined with my left.
ここにあるから
Koko ni arukara
哲学者の石
The Philosopher's Stone,
the Heavenly Stone, the Great Elixir.
天上の石　大エリクシル
賢者の石にいくつもの名前があるように
Just like how the philosopher's stone has many names,
its form isn't always that of a stone.
形状は　石であるとは　かぎらない
マルコーさんが持っていたのは半液体状だった
The one Doctor Marcoh had was almost like a gel.
キンブリーのは鉱石みたいなやつで
Kimblee's looked like a crystal, and it was about this big.
大きさはこれぐらい
Since it possesses so much energy, I pictured something far larger...
ものすごいエネルギーって言うから
もっと大きなものと思っていたが…
I've never seen one bigger than a pebble.
オレは 小石サイズよりでかいのは見たことがない
もっとも
If it's something even larger, that would mean an enormous number of humans was used to create it.
バカでかい賢者の石となると
とんでもない数の人間を材料に使ってそうで…
I'd rather not see one.
できることならお目にかかりたくないね
日本語字幕仕上げ：YUJIN630 VOLENCE
何かを得るためには同等の代価が必要
If one wishes to gain something,
one must present something of equal value.
漫遊字幕組
http://popgo.net/bbs
それが　錬金術の理
That is the principle behind alchemy.
そして　人の世の道理
It is also the principle behind everything else.
次回　鋼の錬金術師
Next time, Fullmetal Alchemist:
FULLMETAL ALCHEMIST
第四十一話 奈落
Episode 41, The Abyss.
甘さは代価としての痛みを少年に求める
His softness seeks pain from the boy as an equal exchange.